37 chapter 38 of black Beauty this LibriVox recording is in the public
domain Black Beauty by Anna Su chapter 38 Dolly and a Real
Gentleman Winter came in early, with a great deal of cold and wet. There was
snow, or sleep or rain almost every day for weeks, changing only for keen driving winds or sharp
frosts. The horses all felt it very much.
When it is a dry cold a couple of good thick rugs will keep the warmth in us;
but when it is soaking rain they soon get wet through and are no good. Some of
the drivers had a waterproof cover to throw over, which was a fine thing; but
some of the men were so poor that they could not protect either themselves or
their horses, and many of them suffered very much that winter. When we horses had worked half
the day we went to our dry stables, and could rest, while they had to sit on
their boxes, sometimes staying out as late as 1 or two in the morning if they
had a party to wait for. When the streets were slippery with
frost or snow that was the worst for all of us
horses. One mile of such traveling, with a weight to draw and no firm footing, would
take more out of us than four on a good road; every nerve and muscle of our
bodies is on the strain to keep our balance; and, added to this, the fear of
falling is more exhausting than anything else. If the roads are very bad indeed
our shoes are roughened but that makes us feel nervous at
first. When the weather was very bad many of the men would go and sit in the
tavern close by, and get someone to watch for them; but they often lost a fair in
that way, and could not, as Jerry said, be there without spending money. He never
went to the Rising Sun; there was a coffee shop near, where he now and then
went, or he bought of an old man, who came
to our rank with tins of hot coffee and pies. It was his opinion that spirits and
beer made a man colder afterward, and that dry clothes, good food, cheerfulness,
and a comfortable wife at home, were the best things to keep a cabman
warm. Polly always supplied him with something to eat when he could not get
home, and sometimes he would see little Dolly peeping from the corner of the
street, to make sure her father” was on the stand. If she saw him she would run off
at full speed and soon come back with something in a tin or basket, some hot
soup or pudding Polly had ready. It was wonderful how such a little
thing could get safely across the street, often thronged with horses and carriages;
but she was a brave little maid, and felt it quite an honor to bring “father's
first course”, as he used to call it. She was a general favorite on the street and
there was not a man who would not have seen her safely across the street, if
Jerry had not been able to do it. One cold windy day Dolly had brought
Jerry a basin of something hot, and was standing by him while he ate it. He had
scarcely begun when a gentleman, walking toward us very fast, held up his umbrella.
Jerry touched his hat in return, gave the basin to Dolly, and was taking off my
cloth, when the gentleman, hastening up, cried out, “No, no, finish your soup, my
friend; I have not much time to spare, but I can wait until you have done, and set
your little girl safe on the pavement.” So saying, he seated himself in the cab.
Jerry thanked him kindly, and came back to Dolly. “There, Dolly, that's a gentleman;
that's a real gentleman, Dolly; he has got time and thought for the comfort of a
poor cabman and a little girl.” Jerry finished his soup, set the
child across, and then took his orders to drive to clap and
Rise. Several times after that the same gentleman took our cab. I think he was
very fond of dogs and horses, for whenever we took him to his own door two
or three dogs would come bounding out to meet him. Sometimes he came around and patted
me, saying in his quiet, pleasant way, “This horse's got a good master, and he deserves
it.” It was a very rare thing for anyone to notice the horse that had been
working for him I've known ladies to do it now and then, and this gentlemen and
one or two others have given me a pat
and a kind word; but 99 persons out of a hundred would as soon think of patting
the steam engine that drew the train. The gentleman was not young, and
there was a forward stoop in his shoulders as if he was always going at
something. His lips were thin and close shut, though they had a very pleasant
smile; his eye was keen, and there was something in his jaw and the motion of
his head that made one think he was very determined in anything he set
about. His voice was pleasant and kind; any horse would trust that voice, though
it was just just as decided as everything else about him. One day he and another gentleman
took our cab; they stopped at a shop in Street, and while his friend went in he
stood at the door. A little ahead of us on the other
side of the street a cart with two very fine horses was standing before some
wine vaults; the carter was not with them, and I cannot tell how long they had been
standing, but they seemed to think they had waited long enough, and began to move off.
Before they had gone many paces the carter came running out and caught them.
He seemed furious at their having moved, and with whip and Rain punished them
brutally, even beating them about the head. Our gentleman saw it all, and
stepping quickly across the street, said in a decided voice: “If you don't stop
that directly, I'll have you arrested for leaving your horses, and for brutal
conduct.” The man, who had clearly been drinking, poured forth some abusive
language, but he left off knocking the horses about, and taking the rains got into his
cart; meantime our friend had quietly taken a notebook from his pocket, and
looking at the name and address painted on the cart, he wrote something
down. “What do you want with that?” growled the carter, as he cracked his whip and
was moving on. A nod and a grim smile was the only answer he
got. On returning to the cab our friend was joined by his companion, who said
laughingly, “I should have thought right you had enough business of your own to
look after, without troubling yourself about other people's horses and
servants.” Our friend stood still for a moment, and throwing his head a little
back, “Do you know why this worlds as bad as it is?” “No,” said the other. “Then I'll
tell you. It is because people think only about their own business, and won't
trouble themselves to stand up for the oppressed, nor bring the wrongdoer to
light. I never see a wicked thing like this without doing what I can, and many a
master has thanked me for letting him know how his horses have been
used.” “I wish there were more gentlemen like you, sir,” said Jerry, “for they are
wanted badly enough in this city.” After this we continued our journey,
and as they got out of the cab our friend was saying, “My doctrine is this,
that if we see cruelty or wrong that we have the power to stop, and do nothing, we
make up ourselves sharers in the
guilt end of chapter